And so we're going to do a little dive into routing.
Who here has sort of a file-based routing, okay?
So it looks like some people here know, which is good.
And so this technique, I think, is starting to take the community
by a storm because as we'll see, it helps, I mean,
I think a lot of development framework work
is around making our developer experience as best as we can.
And simplifying the boilerplate that we have to do.
So for those who don't know, let's take a look
at what we have to start.
So for those, you should already be familiar with view router.
And the fact that with view router,
we have all our pages in the view folder typically speaking.
And then we configure everything inside of our router,
inside of here, inside of a thing called routes.
And we define all these paths, and we define the component that go to it.
And it's a decent amount of work.
Now, file-based routing is interesting because what it says is,
all right, we, this is standard stuff, right?
When the user visits a site, we know, you know,
when they're on a website that they're,
that's actually really small to do here.
When they're on a website, they are going to like,
you know, let's say ardomain.com slash,
and then it's usually some sort of about or like product,
and then the ID, and then maybe like product detail,
something like this.
And if you look at this, this actually looks really, really similar
to how files and directories work.
And so a pattern came out, we're basically there like,
if this is what we want anyways,
why bother with, at least out of the box,
what, with like most case scenario, why are we bothering with all this configuration,
when we can just do it via file-based routing?
And so the way this is going to work is I have installed.
So I took care of some of the setup already.
And part of the reason I did this is because I do think the configuration
is not something I want to harp on.
And so what we're going to be talking about here though,
so I will bring this up so that people do know about this.
Unplug in view router.
So as to, you know, all next generation tech,
this is like the future of tight routing.
And so here you can see how to set up on your own project.
But I've basically done most of this for you.
And so what we're going to do here is I want to show you,
I'm going to progressively kind of start migrating some of it,
and then you all can get a little bit of hands-on experience with it,
as well, to kind of see what it's like.
So first thing first, let's see, I think everything should be ready to go.
Let me just double check real quick.
There's view router, excellent, and then, okay.
So the way this works is, I guess, I guess it can't assume
everyone's background was web here.
But when you visit a website like domain.com like this, just here.
For those of us who come back from like the FTV days and we understand how this stuff works,
what you don't know is what you're actually hitting is index.html.
So similarly, if we go to domain.com slash product,
right, and then you have like a bunch of products that are on the page,
you're really hitting products.index.ml.
The reason this is useful context is because you're going to need to know this
when you're doing the file based routing, because you're basically going to be calling these files,
index.view, and so forth.
So what we do is here is we're going to create a folder here called pages,
rather than views. And so to show that this works, I'm going to go ahead and first move the home page
inside of here. And so this is going to break up under stuff because this no longer exists.
So I'm going to delete this route. And then what we need to do is inside of this,
I need to import routes in this thing called handle hot updates. So I'll explain a second
from view router slash auto routes. So this is like a package within it.
Now we have a naming collision here. So we're going to use our handy little
rename here. So I'm going to call this auto routes. That's what's happening. They're being auto
generated. And then we're going to do here is that the routes, we're going to merge them. We're
going to say first go ahead and do all your routes or actually we're going to do auto routes. First,
then we're going to merge that with the routes that we manually wrote ourselves here. So that's
what's happening there. So these are being spread across the same object. And then this is just a
configuration thing. But basically this will allow us when we're doing hot module reloading.
So that the router actually is generating the right thing. So is it hot updates? Hot update. There you go.
Okay, perfect. Now if this works as intended,
yeah, reloaded. Locate host. 5173. Okay, beautiful. It's broken. That's good. What we did
is we said, hey, our pages are route. If you notice it's called homepage, not index. But if we go
to homepage like this, now all of us on everything shows up. So just a demo this, I'm going to switch
this now back to index.view. You can see it's going to generate. And then if we now home page can't
be found, if we go to the home page now, voila. Now it's the home page. And what's cool is that you didn't
see it here, but this file here is actually being generated for you this whole time. As you
to be clear, do not modify this file. Big warning. But I could tell our router and you see bigger than that.
But you can see here, it's actually generating typed routes so that when you're actually equating
these up, you don't actually do some records, autocomplete. Don't ask me to explain how the
typed route works. Just know that it's supposed to be typed safe. Let's end advantagey get with this.
And so then I'm going to go ahead and just do like one more, for example. So we mentioned like
a tax detail page, right? So a tax detail page, this is the funny thing about the tax detail page,
is that I actually like, without looking at the route, it's hard to into it what exactly
you intended with that. And so I have to kind of come back in here. I mean, look at this,
for example, task details page is under task slash and then a dynamic parameter of ID. Whereas
weak, let's see, the weak detail page, weak detail page is actually under planar, weak ID.
And so this is actually kind of an interesting byproduct of doing it, the file-based routing
way is that your router, your company's actually get pretty declarative and you understand where
they're supposed to be and what they intend to do. And so the way this particular works,
so I'm going to do the task one. So I'm going to go ahead and let's see, I'm going to move
to move the task page. Oh wait, that's the wrong one. Task page in here. Yes, just move.
And then so task page is gone. Then I'm going to do the task detail page in here.
That's going to be gone now. And then to finalize this, we're going to go ahead and we're going
to create a task folder because that's the route we wanted. And then we'll drop the detail page in
there. And then the convention we're looking for here to tell you all that is the square bracket
inside of your file name basically marked the fact that it's a dynamic parameter. And so if you
did something like this, by the way, so just then this would be the task would be static,
like the task dash, and then whatever is appended is basically the parameter.
So there's that. And then task page, I'm just going to put inside of here as index, whoops.
Not view X, okay. And then I think, uh, dot, dot, dot, dot, dot, dot, dot.
Okay, great. Don't say, okay, let's see. Fresh routes, planners correct. Nope, that's good.
Uh, planner. Wait, planner. Yeah, somehow updated that. Oh, yeah, that's weird. Okay. So that should be this.
That looks good. I think, okay, why is it unhappy? Oh, routes, that's yes. Okay.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, here you are.
Yes, good, plan our page.
Panerplage view.
Oh, no, it somehow updated my directory path.
Should be views.
Views views.
No tasks.
Oh, tasks as well.
Just views.
Oh, you're right.
Thank you.
Hey, beautiful.
OK, so now you can see if we go to tasks.
Whoa, what's this happen?
Oh, I know what just happened.
We go to the tasks index page.
I believe that the imports and mess up.
Oh, no, they're good.
Your task list filter.
Yeah, it looks like the task list filter tasks.
Oh, yeah, yeah, yeah, I did this experiment.
And then I never fixed it.
Store that task list.
Not a task, there you go.
OK, refresh, aha, here we go.
OK, and then you can see here.
Boom, task one is the ID.
Is everything works?
And what's great now is that whereas in the past,
remember I was like, oh, I need to create a sandbox page
and I have to configure bunch of stuff.
Now it can be like, I don't know.
Someone shot out a page name for me.
All right, sandbox, though, do we have one already?
I think we have one.
I'll call Playground.
PlaygroundW.
Yay.
Playground.
Done.
All that boilerplate gone.
I don't have to deal with it anymore.
I love it.
These are the things that made me happy.